<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="hadoop">
  
  <title>Spring and Hadoop</title>

  <para>One of the common tasks when using Hadoop is interacting with its <emphasis>runtime</emphasis> - whether it is a local setup or a remote cluster, one needs to properly configure and bootstrap Hadoop
  in order to submit the required jobs. This chapter will focus on how Spring Hadoop (SHDP) leverages Spring's lightweight IoC container to simplify the interaction with Hadoop and make deployment, testing and provisioning
  easier and more manageable.</para>
  
  <section id="hadoop:ns">
  	<title>Using the Spring Hadoop Namespace</title>
  	
  	<para>To simplify configuration, SHDP provides a dedicated namespace for most of its components. However, one can opt to configure the beans
  	directly through the usual <literal>&lt;bean&gt;</literal> definition. For more information about XML Schema-based configuration in Spring, see 
  	<ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/xsd-config.html">this</ulink> appendix in the
  	Spring Framework reference documentation.</para>
  	
  	<para>To use the SHDP namespace, one just needs to import it inside the configuration:</para>

 	<programlistingco>
 		<areaspec>
 			<area id="hdp#ns#prefix" coords="4 11"/>
 			<area id="hdp#ns#uri" coords="4 58"/>
 			<area id="hdp#ns#uri#loc" coords="7 119"/>
 			<area id="hdp#ns#example" coords="10 9"/>
 		</areaspec>
 		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:hdp="http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop"
	xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop/spring-hadoop.xsd">
	<bean id ... >
	
    <hdp:configuration ...>
		
</beans>]]></programlisting>
 		<calloutlist>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#ns#prefix">
 				<para>Spring Hadoop namespace prefix. Any name can do but through out the reference documentation, the <literal>hdp</literal> will be used.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#ns#uri">
 				<para>The namespace URI.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#ns#uri#loc">
 				<para>The namespace URI location. Note that even though the location points to an external address (which exists and is valid), Spring will resolve
 				the schema locally as it is included in the Spring Hadoop library.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#ns#example">
 				<para>Declaration example for the Hadoop namespace. Notice the prefix usage.</para>
 			</callout>
 		</calloutlist>
 	</programlistingco>
 	
 	<para>Once declared, the namespace elements can be declared simply by appending the aforementioned prefix. Note that is possible to change the default namespace,
 	for example from <literal>&lt;beans&gt;</literal> to <literal>&lt;hdp&gt;</literal>. This is useful for configuration composed mainly of Hadoop components as
 	it avoids declaring the prefix. To achieve this, simply swap the namespace prefix declaration above:</para>

 	<programlistingco>
 		<areaspec>
 			<area id="hdp#default-ns#prefix" coords="2 64"/>
 			<area id="hdp#default-ns#beans-prefix" coords="3 64"/>
 			<area id="hdp#default-ns#beans-example" coords="9 64"/>
 			<area id="hdp#default-ns#hdp-example" coords="11 64"/>
 		</areaspec>
 		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans:beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:beans="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
	xsi:schemaLocation="
	    http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
	    http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop http://www.springframework.org/schema/gemfire/spring-hadoop.xsd">
	    
    <beans:bean id ... >
	
    <configuration ...>
	
</beans:beans>]]></programlisting>
 		<calloutlist>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#default-ns#prefix">
 				<para>The default namespace declaration for this XML file points to the Spring Hadoop namespace.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#default-ns#beans-prefix">
 				<para>The beans namespace prefix declaration.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#default-ns#beans-example">
 				<para>Bean declaration using the <literal>&lt;beans&gt;</literal> namespace. Notice the prefix.</para>
 			</callout>
 			<callout arearefs="hdp#default-ns#hdp-example">
 				<para>Bean declaration using the <literal>&lt;hdp&gt;</literal> namespace. Notice the <emphasis>lack</emphasis> of prefix (as <literal>hdp</literal> is the default namespace).</para>
 			</callout>
 		</calloutlist>
 	</programlistingco>
 	
 	<para>For the remainder of this doc, to improve readability, the XML examples will simply refer to the <literal>&lt;hdp&gt;</literal> namespace
 	without the namespace declaration, where possible.</para>
  </section>
  
   <section id="hadoop:config">
   	 <title>Configuring Hadoop</title>
   	 
   	 <para>In order to use Hadoop, one needs to first configure it namely by creating a <literal>Configuration</literal> object. The configuration holds information about the job tracker, the input, output format and the various
   	 other parameters of the map reduce job.</para>
   	 
   	 <para>In its simplest form, the configuration definition is a one liner:</para>
   	 
   	 <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<hdp:configuration />]]></programlisting>
   	 
   	 <para>The declaration above defines a <classname>Configuration</classname> bean (to be precise a factory bean of type <classname>ConfigurationFactoryBean</classname>) named, by default, 
   	 <literal>hadoop-configuration</literal>. The default name is used, by conventions, by the other elements that require a configuration - this leads to simple and very concise configurations as the 
   	 main components can automatically wire themselves up without requiring any specific configuration.</para>
   	 
   	 <para>For scenarios where the defaults need to be tweaked, one can pass in additional configuration files:</para>
   	 
   	 <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<hdp:configuration resources="classpath:/custom-site.xml, classpath:/hq-site.xml"]]></programlisting>
   	 
   	 <para>In this example, two additional Hadoop configuration resources are added to the configuration.</para>
   	 
    <note>
        <para>Note that the configuration makes use of Spring's <ulink
        url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/resources.html"><interfacename>Resource</interfacename></ulink>
        abstraction to locate the file. This allows various search patterns to be used, depending on the running environment or the prefix specified
        (if any) by the value - in this example the classpath is used.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In addition to referencing configuration resources, one can tweak Hadoop settings directly through Java <classname>Properties</classname>. 
    This can be quite handy when just a few options need to be changed:</para>
    
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:hdp="http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop/spring-hadoop.xsd">
        
     <hdp:configuration>
        <entry key="fs.default.name" value="hdfs://localhost:9000"/>
        <entry key="hadoop.tmp.dir" value="/tmp/hadoop"/>
     </hdp:configuration>
</beans>]]></programlisting>

     <para>One can further customize the settings by avoiding the so called <emphasis>hard-coded</emphasis> values by externalizing them so they can be replaced at runtime, based on the existing
     environment without touching the configuration:</para>
     
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:hdp="http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop"
    xmlns:context="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/context http://www.springframework.org/schema/context/spring-context.xsd
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop http://www.springframework.org/schema/hadoop/spring-hadoop.xsd">
        
     <hdp:configuration>
        <entry key="fs.default.name" value="${hd.fs}"/>
        <entry key="hadoop.tmp.dir" value="file://${java.io.tmpdir}"/>
     </hdp:configuration>
     
     <context:property-placeholder location="classpath:hadoop.properties" />     
</beans>]]></programlisting>
     
     <para>
     Through Spring's property placeholder <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/beans.html#beans-factory-placeholderconfigurer">support</ulink>, <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/expressions.html">SpEL</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/2011/06/09/spring-framework-3-1-m2-released/">environment 
     abstraction</ulink> one can externalize environment specific properties from the main code base easing the deployment across multiple machines. In the example above, the default file system is
     replaced based on the properties available in <literal>hadoop.properties</literal> while the temp dir is determined dynamically through <literal>SpEL</literal>. Both approaches offer a lot
     of flexbility in adapting to the running environment - in fact we use this approach extensivly in the Spring Hadoop test suite to cope with the differences between the different development boxes
     and the CI server.</para>
     
     <para><anchor id="hadoop:config:inherit"/>It is possible to create configuration based on existing ones - this allows one to create dedicated configurations, slightly different from the main ones, usable for certain jobs 
     (such as streaming - more about that below). Simply use the <literal>configuration-ref</literal> attribute to refer to the <emphasis>parent</emphasis> configuration - all its properties will be inherited and
     overridden as specified by the child:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<!-- default name is 'hadoop-configuration' -->
<hdp:configuration>
    <entry key="fs.default.name" value="${hd.fs}"/>
    <entry key="hadoop.tmp.dir" value="file://${java.io.tmpdir}"/>
</hdp:configuration>
     
<hdp:configuration id="custom" configuration-ref="hadoop-configuration">
    <entry key="fs.default.name" value="${custom.hd.fs}"/>
</hdp:configuration>     

...
]]></programlisting>     
     <para>Make sure though you specify a different name since otherwise, since both definitions will have the same name, the Spring container will interpret this as being the same
     definition (and will usually consider the last one found).</para>
     
     <para>Another option worth mentioning is <literal>register-url-handler</literal> which, as the name implies, automatically registers an URL handler in the running VM. This allows urls referrencing 
     <emphasis>hdfs</emphasis> resource (by using the <literal>hdfs</literal> prefix) to be properly resolved - if the handler is not registered, such an URL would through an exception since the VM does not know what 
     <literal>hdfs</literal> mean.</para>
     <note><para>Since only one URL handler can be registered per VM, at most once, this option is turned off by default. Due to the reasons mentioned before, once enabled if it fails, it will log the error but will not
     throw an exception. If your <literal>hdfs</literal> URLs stop working, make sure to investigate this aspect.</para></note>
   </section>
   
   <section id="hadoop:job">
   	 <title>Creating a Hadoop Job</title>
   	 
   	 <para>Once the Hadoop configuration is taken care of, one needs to actually submit some work to it. SHDP makes it easy to configure and run Hadoop jobs whether they are vanilla map-reduce type or streaming.
   	 Let us start with an example:</para>
   	 
   	 <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<hdp:job id="mr-job" 
  input-path="/input/" output-path="/ouput/"
  mapper="org.apache.hadoop.examples.WordCount.TokenizerMapper"
  reducer="org.apache.hadoop.examples.WordCount.IntSumReducer"/>]]></programlisting>
   	 
   	 <para>The declaration above creates a typical Hadoop <literal>Job</literal>: specifies its input and output, the mapper and the reducer classes. Notice that there is no reference to the Hadoop configuration above - that's
   	 because, if not specified, the default naming convention (<literal>hadoop-configuration</literal>) will be used instead. Neither are the key or value types - these two are automatically determined through a best-effort attempt
   	 by analyzing the class information of the mapper and the reducer. Of course, these settings can be overridden: the former through the <literal>configuration-ref</literal> element, the latter through <literal>key</literal> and
   	 <literal>value</literal> attributes.
   	 There are plenty of options available not shown in the example (for simplicity) such as the sort or group comparator, the combiner, the partitioner, the codecs to use or the input/output format just to name a few - 
   	 they are supported, just take a look at the SHDP schema (<xref linkend="appendix-schema"/>) or simply trigger auto-completion (usually <literal>ALT+SPACE</literal>) in your IDE; if it supports XML namespaces and is properly configured it will display the
   	 available elements.</para>
   	 
   	 <note>
   	 	<para>The job definition can validate the existance of the input and output paths before submitting the actual job (which is slow), to prevent its failure. Take a look at <emphasis>validate-paths</emphasis> attribute
   	 	to avoid these errors early on without having to touch the job tracker only to get an exception.</para>
   	 </note>

	 <section id="hadoop:job:streaming">
	 	<title>Creating a Hadoop Streaming Job</title>
	 	
	 	<para>Hadoop <ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/current/streaming.html">Streaming</ulink> jobs (or in short streaming), are a popular feature of Hadoop as they allow the creation of Map/Reduce jobs
	 	with any executable or script (the equivalent of using the previous counting words example is to use <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat_%28Unix%29"><literal>cat</literal></ulink> and 
	 	<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wc_%28Unix%29"><literal>wc</literal></ulink> commands).
	 	While it is rather easy to start up Streaming from the command line, doing so programatically, such as from a Java environment, can be challenging due to the various number of parameters (and their ordering) 
	 	that need to be parsed. SHDP simplifies such as tasks - it's as easy and straight-forward as declaring a <literal>job</literal> from the previous section; in fact most of the attributes will be the same:</para>
	 	
   	 <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<hdp:streaming id="streaming" 
  input-path="/input/" output-path="/ouput/"
  mapper="${path.cat}" reducer="${path.wc}"/>]]></programlisting>
	 	
	 	<para>If certain properties need to be specified (typically the <literal>-D</literal> or <literal>-cmdenv</literal> arguments), consider creating a dedicated configuration object as documented 
	 	<link linkend="hadoop:config:inherit">above</link> and using that for the streaming job.</para>
	 </section>   	 
   </section>
</chapter>