<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="getting-started"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Overview of Spring Hadoop</title>

  <para>This chapter describes the various components that Spirng Hadoop uses
  and builds upon.</para>

  <section label="overview-batch">
    <title>Spring Batch</title>

    <para>Spring Batch is an Apache 2.0 open source project that enables large
    organizations to develop customized enterprise batch applications
    essential to their daily operations. It provides out of the box handling
    of common batch scenarios such as automatic retries after failure,
    periodic commits synchronous and asynchronous processing, non-sequential
    processing, job tracking, and restart. It also contains several components
    for parsing, mapping, reading and writing data to and from various
    traditional data sources, for example flat files, relational databases,
    and messaging systems as well as an admin console and associated web
    application. It used in production in many mission critical environments
    across a range of industriers.</para>

    <para>Spring Batch It is developed by SpringSource in collaboration with
    Accenture. The first 1.0 release was made in 2007 and is now at version
    2.2.x. It has been designed with extensibility in mind. The Spring Hadoop
    hooks into those extensibility points so that in addition to interacting
    with traditional data sources in an enterprise batch job, Spring Batch
    jobs can now interact with a wide range of Hadoop projects, from HDFS and
    map-reduce, to Hive, Pig, and HBase. </para>

    <para>To learn more about Spring Batch, visit the <link
    ns6:href="http://static.springsource.org/spring-batch/">Spring Batch
    project page</link>. There are also two books available.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link ns6:href="http://www.manning.com/templier/">Spring Batch
        in Action</link> - October 2011 - Manning</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link ns6:href="http://www.apress.com/9781430234524">Pro Spring
        Batch</link> - July 18, 2011 - APress</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A <link
    ns6:href="http://www.manning.com/free/green_templier.html">free
    introduction chapter</link> is available from the the Spring Batch in
    Action book.</para>
  </section>

  <section label="overview-integration">
    <title>Spring Integration</title>

    <para>TBD</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Spring Data</title>

    <para>TBD</para>
  </section>

  <section label="overview-spring">
    <title>Spring Framework</title>

    <para>TBD</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
