<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="requirements"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Requirements</title>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop requires JDK level 6.0 (just like Hadoop) and
  above, Spring <ulink
  url="http://www.springsource.org/about">Framework</ulink> 3.0 (3.2
  recommended) and above and is built against <ulink
  url="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Apache Hadoop</ulink> 1.2.1. SHDP supports
  and is <ulink
  url="https://build.springsource.org/browse/SPRINGDATAHADOOP">tested</ulink>
  daily against Apache Hadoop 1.2.1 and also against 1.0.4 and 1.1.2 as well
  as against various Hadoop distributions: <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.cloudera.com/">Cloudera</ulink> CDH3
        (cdh3u5), CDH4 (cdh4.1.3 MRv1) distributions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.hortonworks.com/">Hortonworks</ulink>
        Data Platform 1.3</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.greenplum.com/">Greenplum</ulink> HD
        (1.2)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>Any distro compatible with Apache Hadoop 1.x should be
  supported.</para>

  <para>We have recently added support to allow 2.0.x based distributions to
  be used with the current functionality. We are running test builds against
  Apache Hadoop 2.0.5-alpha, Pivotal HD 1.0 and Hortonworks Data Platform 2.0.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>Hadoop YARN support is only available in Spring for Apache Hadoop
    version 2.0 and later.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Spring Data Hadoop is provided out of the box and it is certified to
  work on Greenplum and Pivotal HD distributions.</para>

  <para>Instructions for setting up project builds using various supported
  distributions are provided on the Spring for Apache Hadoop wiki -<ulink
  url="http://cascading.org/" /><ulink url="http://hbase.apache.org/" /><ulink
  url="http://hive.apache.org/" /> <ulink
  url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-hadoop/wiki">https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-hadoop/wiki</ulink></para>

  <para>Regarding Hadoop-related projects, SDHP supports <ulink
  url="http://cascading.org/">Cascading</ulink> 2.1, <ulink
  url="http://hbase.apache.org/">HBase</ulink> 0.90.x, <ulink
  url="http://hive.apache.org/">Hive</ulink> 0.8.x and <ulink
  url="http://pig.apache.org/">Pig</ulink> 0.9.x and above. As a rule of
  thumb, when using Hadoop-related projects, such as Hive or Pig, use the
  required Hadoop version as a basis for discovering the supported
  versions.</para>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop also requires a Hadoop installation up and
  running. If you don't already have a Hadoop cluster up and running in your
  environment, a good first step is to create a single-node cluster. To
  install Hadoop 1.2.1, the "<link
  ns6:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/stable/#Getting+Started">Getting
  Started"</link> page from the official Apache documentation is a good
  general guide. If you are running on Ubuntu, the tutorial from Michael G.
  Noll, "<link
  ns6:href="http://www.michael-noll.com/tutorials/running-hadoop-on-ubuntu-linux-single-node-cluster/">Running
  Hadoop On Ubuntu Linux (Single-Node Cluster)</link>" provides more details.
  It is also convenient to download a Virtual Machine where Hadoop is setup
  and ready to go. Cloudera, Hortonworks and Pivotal all provide virtual
  machines and provide VM downloads on their product pages. Additionally, the
  <link linkend="appendices">appendix</link> provides information on how to
  use Spring for Apache Hadoop and setup Hadoop with cloud providers, such as
  Amazon Web Services.</para>
</chapter>
