<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="requirements"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Requirements</title>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop requires JDK level 6.0 (just like Hadoop) and
  above, Spring <ulink
  url="http://www.springsource.org/about">Framework</ulink> 3.0 (3.2
  recommended) and above and <ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Apache
  Hadoop</ulink> 0.20.2 (1.0.4 or 1.1.2 recommended) and above. SHDP supports
  and is <ulink
  url="https://build.springsource.org/browse/SPRINGDATAHADOOP">tested</ulink>
  daily against Apache Hadoop 1.0.4 and Apache Hadoop 1.1.2 as well as against
  various Hadoop distributions: 
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.cloudera.com/">Cloudera</ulink> CDH3 (CD3u5),
      CDH4 (CDH4.1u3 MRv1) distributions</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.hortonworks.com/">Hortonworks</ulink> Data
      Platform 1.3</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.greenplum.com/">Greenplum</ulink> HD
      (1.2)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  Any distro compatible with Apache Hadoop 1.0.x should be
  supported.</para>

  <para>Spring Data Hadoop is provided out of the box and it is certified to
  work on Greenplum and Pivotal HD distributions.</para>

  <warning>
     Note that Hadoop YARN and Hadoop 2.0.x (currently in alpha stage), is not explicitly supported yet, but we have added support to allow 2.0.x based distributions to be used with the current functionality. We are running some limited test builds against Apache Hadoop 2.0.4-alpha, Pivotal HD 1.0 and Hortonworks Data Platform 2.0. 
  </warning>

  <para>Regarding Hadoop-related projects, SDHP supports <ulink
  url="http://cascading.org/">Cascading</ulink> 2.1, <ulink
  url="http://hbase.apache.org/">HBase</ulink> 0.90.x, <ulink
  url="http://hive.apache.org/">Hive</ulink> 0.8.x and <ulink
  url="http://pig.apache.org/">Pig</ulink> 0.9.x and above. As a rule of
  thumb, when using Hadoop-related projects, such as Hive or Pig, use the
  required Hadoop version as a basis for discovering the supported
  versions.</para>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop also requires a Hadoop installation up and
  running. If you don't already have a Hadoop cluster up and running in your
  environment, a good first step is to create a single-node cluster. To
  install Hadoop 1.1.2, the <link
  ns6:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/stable/#Getting+Started">Getting
  Started</link> page from the official Apache documentation is a good general
  guide. If you are running on Ubuntu, the tutorial from Michael G. Noll,
  "<link
  ns6:href="http://www.michael-noll.com/tutorials/running-hadoop-on-ubuntu-linux-single-node-cluster/">Running
  Hadoop On Ubuntu Linux (Single-Node Cluster)</link>" provides more details.
  It is also convenient to download a Virtual Machine where Hadoop is setup
  and ready to go. Cloudera provides virtual machines of various formats <link
  ns6:href="https://ccp.cloudera.com/display/SUPPORT/Cloudera%27s+Hadoop+Demo+VM">here</link>.
  You can also download the <link
  ns6:href="http://www.greenplum.com/products/greenplum-hd">EMC Greenplum
  HD</link> distribution or download one of <link
  ns6:href="http://hortonworks.com/products/hortonworksdataplatform/">Hortonworks
  distributions</link>. Additionally, the <link
  linkend="appendices">appendix</link> provides information on how to use
  Spring for Apache Hadoop and setup Hadoop with cloud providers, such as
  Amazon Web Services.</para>
</chapter>
