<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="requirements"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Requirements</title>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop 2.1 is built and tested with JDK 7.0 (generated jars are usable in JDK 6.0 and above), <ulink
  url="http://projects.spring.io/spring-framework/">Spring Framework</ulink> 4.0 and
  is by default built against <ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Apache
  Hadoop</ulink> 2.5.1.</para>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop 2.1 supports the following versions and distributions: <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Apache Hadoop</ulink> 
        2.4.1 *</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Apache Hadoop</ulink> 
        2.5.1 *</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.gopivotal.com/">Pivotal</ulink> HD
        2.1 *</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.cloudera.com/">Cloudera</ulink> CDH5
        (2.5.0-cdh5.2.0) *</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.hortonworks.com/">Hortonworks</ulink>
        Data Platform 2.1 *</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>* The distributions noted with and asterisk will include spring-yarn support in the build.</para>
    <para>Any distribution compatible with Apache Hadoop 2.2.x or later should be usable.</para>
  </para>

  <para>Spring for Apache Hadoop 2.1 is tested daily against a number of Hadoop distributions. See the <ulink
  url="https://build.spring.io/browse/SPRINGDATAHADOOP">test plan page</ulink> for current status.</para>

  <para>Instructions for setting up project builds using various supported
  distributions are provided on the Spring for Apache Hadoop wiki - <ulink
  url="https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-hadoop/wiki">https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-hadoop/wiki</ulink></para>

  <para>Regarding Hadoop-related projects, SDHP supports <ulink
  url="http://hbase.apache.org/">HBase</ulink> 0.94.11, <ulink
  url="http://hive.apache.org/">Hive</ulink> 0.11.0 and <ulink
  url="http://pig.apache.org/">Pig</ulink> 0.11.0 and above. As a rule of
  thumb, when using Hadoop-related projects, such as Hive or Pig, use the
  required Hadoop version as a basis for discovering the supported
  versions.</para>

  <para>To take full advantage of Spring for Apache Hadoop you need a
  running Hadoop cluster. If you don't already have one in your
  environment, a good first step is to create a single-node cluster. To
  install the most recent stable verision of Hadoop, the "<link
  ns6:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/stable/#Getting+Started">Getting
  Started"</link> page from the official Apache documentation is a good
  general guide. There should be a link for "Single Node Setup".</para>

  <para>
  It is also convenient to download a Virtual Machine where Hadoop is setup
  and ready to go. Cloudera, Hortonworks and Pivotal all provide virtual
  machines and provide VM downloads on their product pages. Additionally, the
  <link linkend="appendices">appendix</link> provides information on how to
  use Spring for Apache Hadoop and setup Hadoop with cloud providers, such as
  Amazon Web Services.</para>
</chapter>
